A Guide to the Film collection FA466
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Rockefeller Foundation, 18
  - Proytecto Puebla, CIMMYT, Sound, Color, 25 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel II 50.6 F1, Reel AV 152)
    Educational film which describes the planting, fertilization, plowing, spraying, harvesting, and marketing of corn at the Puebla Project.
  - Rice (Original camera footage), 1963; Silent, Color, 12 reels in total, varying lengths. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 17, Reel AV 16, Reel AV 19, Reel AV 18, Reel AV 26, Reel AV 25, Reel II 50.6 Fe 29 - II 50.6 Fe 40, Reel AV 15, Reel AV 21, Reel AV 20, Reel AV 23, Reel AV 22)
    Unedited film footage shot throughout Southeast Asia: the Philippines, Japan, India, Thailand and Bali. Shot in 1963 for the RF film "Rice" (completed film not available at the Rockefeller Archive Center).
  - Rockefeller Foundation: Episode of The Today Show, 1964 April 27; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 43, Reel II 50.6 Fe 51)
    J.G. Harrar and JDR 3rd being interviewed by James Daly and Maureen O'Sullivan. Part of publicity for the RF 50th anniversary and the publication of "Toward the Well-being of Mankind". Questions about JDR 3rd's personal giving as well as family legacy of philanthropy.
  - The Sardinian Project, 1948; Sound, Black & white, 35 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 42, Reel II 50.6 Fe 57, Box 1, Dvd AV 42)
    This is the first half of a film which shows the campaign "Ente Regionale per la Lotta Anti-Anofelica en Sardengna (Regional Organization for the Anti-Anopheles or ERLAAS)" in Sardinia. Footage of village life, rampant malaria and its treatment with DDT spray. Produced by the Shell Oil Company. (The second half of the film is "Adventure in Sardinia").
  - Speaking Freely: Foundations and Philanthropy, 1968; Sound, Black & white, 55 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 49, Reel II 50.6 Fe 64)
    Film in two parts: J.G. Harrar, president of the RF, being interviewed by Edwin Newman on NBC. Questions: How do foundations give away money? How do you measure success? What is the RF position on giving the public correct information and avoiding propaganda?
  - The Unconquered Plague: Schistosomiasis: Campaign in the Caribbean 1915-1924, Sound, Color, 25 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel II 50.6 F 2, Reel AV 147, Box 1, Dvd AV 147)
    Filmed by Jack Wolfgang Beck in St. Lucia, introducing the disease, its symptoms and means of infection, and the methodologies being used to research and treat the population. Laboratory work, experiments with mice, pesticide usage, construction to avoid infected areas and to make clean water available, and a series of interviews and footage exploring the assimilation of health education, methods taught to the public, and so on.
  - Unhooking the Hookworm, c. 1920; Silent, Black & white, 10 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel II 50.6 Fd 1, Reel AV 123, Box 1, Dvd AV 123)
    Field and lab footage from the RF campaign to eradicate hookworm in the American South, showing the symptoms, diagnosis and treatment of hookworm. Includes scenes of environments where the disease exists and methods of prevention. Also includes some graphic imagery of the male and female worms and their parasitic behavior in humans.
    Two copies of access DVD. Two copies of .mov data disk.
  - War on Mosquitoes, c. 1940-1950s; Sound, Black & white, 11 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel II 50.6 Fb 1, Reel AV 112)
    Produced by the Brazilian Ministry of Education and Health, showing cooperative actions with the Rockefeller Foundation to combat malaria. Presents problem of mosquitoes in Brazil and the methods of control: filling in water holes, spraying pesticides, laboratory work, mapping sites.
- Rockefeller University, 19
  Contains films originating from Rockefeller University records, as well as various laboratories and the papers of select faculty.
  - 1972 Nobel Prize in Chemistry, Sound, Color, 20 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 M786 Fe 1, Reel AV 705)
    Film of a meeting between Christian B. Anfinsen (National Institute of Health), Stanford Moore (Rockefeller University), and William H. Stein (Rockefeller University).
  - Biochemistry of Heredity, c. 1958-1960; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 T189 Fe 2, Reel AV 729)
    Episode of NBC series Continental Classroom
  - Christmas Lecture 1965/1966: Dr. Allfrey, Silent, Color, 5 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 M679 Fb 3, Reel AV 674)
  - Christmas Lecture 1965/1966: Dr. Mirsky, Silent, Color, 10 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 675, Reel I 450 M679 Fb 4)
  - Christmas Lecture 1965/1966: Dr. Mirsky, Dr. Allfrey, Dr. Coldrum, Silent, Color, 9 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 676, Reel I 450 M679 Fb 5)
  - Christmas Lecture 1965/1966: Nuclear Isolation, Silent, Color, 5 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 M679 Fb 1, Reel AV 672)
    Recording of lecture by Dr. Mirsky on nuclear isolation, autolytic enzymes, red cells, and related experiments.
  - Dr. Lyman C. Craig, Sound, Black & white, 27 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 C844 Fe 1, Reel AV 731)
    Episode of NBC series Continental Classroom with Dr. Lyman
  - Dr. Lyman C. Craig Films, Silent, Color, Varying lengths. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 629- AV 634, AV 668-671, AV 731, AV 670A, Reel I 450 C844 Fa 1- Fe 1)
  - DNA Extraction, Silent, Color, 2 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 673, Reel I 450 M679 Fb 2)
    Part of lecture by Dr. Mirsky on DNA centrifuge.
  - Experimental Epidemiology, Silent, Black & white. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 W395 Fe 1, Reel AV 724)
    An investigation of the causes which determine the prevalence of epidemic diseases, from Rockefeller University faculty member Leslie T. Webster.
  - The Future of Medicine, 1966 May; Sound, Color, 25 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 728, Reel I 450 T189 Fe 1)
    NBC television program from 1966 May about molecular biology, nucleic acids, and the new Merck Building.
  - Muscle Transportation in the Rat (Reel I 450 W435 Fb 64, Reel AV 549)
  - Nerve Fiber Motion, Silent, Black & white. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 W 436 Fb 27, Reel AV 512)
  - Principles of Genetics Lecture Series
    - Genetic Loads in Mendelian Populations, Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 789)
      Lecture by Dr. T. Dobzhansky, Columbia University (#25 in series)
    - Mutegen-Induced Gene Mutation, Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 787)
      Lecture by Dr. H. J. Muller, Indiana University (#23 in series)
    - The Origin of Species, Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 770)
      Lecture by Dr. G. L. Stebbins, University of California (#28 in series)
    - Selection, Genetic Death, and Genetic Radiation Damage, Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 769)
      Lecture by Dr. T. Dobzhansky, Columbia University (#26 in series)
    - Virus Genetics: Bacteriophage (AV #774), Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. Only available on 16mm film. (Reel AV 774)
      Lecture by Dr. J. Lederberg, Stanford University (#46 in series)
    - Virus Genetics: Plant and Animal Viruses, Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. Only available on 16mm film. (Reel AV 776)
      Lecture by Dr. J. Lederberg, Stanford University (#47 in series)
  - Profile of Dr. Dubos, 1970; Sound, Color, 18 minutes. Only available on 16mm film. (Reel I 450 D851, Reel AV 736)
    From WABC-TV with reporter Melba Tolliver visiting Dr. Rene Dubos in his RU laboratory and office. Discusses high school and local history, walk through neighborhood with wife Jean Dubos.
  - Reminiscences of Early Days of the Medical School, 1932; Sound, Black & white, 12 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 216.3 Fe 1, Reel AV 834)
    Interview with Dr. William Welch about John Hopkins University
  - Rene Dubos' Provocative New York, 1969; Sound, Color, 15 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 D851, Reel AV 737)
    Interview of Dr. Rene Dubos by reporter Earl Ubel (WCBS-TV) at RU campus. Discusses destruction of the environment, mismanagement of urban life, deterioration of the city, child development, effects of pollution on children, and the East River Drive waterfront.
- Paul Ehrlich, 20
  - Syphilis and Salvarsan, 1948; Silent, Black & white, 7 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel RU RG 650.3 EH89, Reel AV 1872)
    A brief introduction to the early prognosis and treatment methods for syphilis. Medical names, equipment, and methods are discussed.
- Paul A. Weiss Laboratory, 21
  The RAC has a collection of some 500 films with minimal descriptive or technical information; most are views of chemical samples through a microscope and related laboratory processes, although there is some footage of lectures and presentations by Dr. Weiss. Original can notations include such titles as Salam Nerve Fiber, Margins of Liver and Kidney Cells, and Cleveland Lecture.
  Dr. Weiss was a biologist and professor who worked at the Rockefeller University for over 15 years.
  Arranged as received, in original order.
  - Dr. Paul A. Weiss Laboratory Films, 500 films. Silent, Black & white, varying lengths. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel I 450 W436 Fa 166 - I 450 W436 Fe 4, Reel AV 153-AV 667)
- William H. Whyte, 22
  As the mentor for initiatives such as the Project for Public Spaces and the Street Life Project in the 1960’s and 1970’s, William H. Whyte based his theories about urban planning and social movement on hours of footage and time-lapse photographs.
  The collection of edited and raw films held at the RAC come from Whyte’s work with the American Conservation Association and his role as an advisor to Laurance Rockefeller. A majority of the Whyte films are unedited trims and original clips, compiled into final films at a later date.
  - Assembly for Japan Society: Tokyo/New York Pedestrians, 1987 May; Silent, Color, 29 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1127)
    Unedited footage of various public areas in New York City and Tokyo, shot in regular speed and time lapse.
  - Pilot A Outtakes (100% Conversation), Silent, Color, 7 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1132)
    Unedited footage from various public parks throughout New York City; some duplicate footage as seen in AV #1125.
  - Plaza, Part 1, Silent, Color, 10 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1129)
    Unedited footage from various public parks throughout New York City; some duplicate footage as seen in AV #1125
  - Plaza, Part 3, Silent, Color, 9 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1130)
  - The Social Life of Small Urban Spaces, 1979; Sound, Color, 55 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1125)
    A finished film written and narrated by Whyte, examining trends in social movement based on footage shot throughout New York City and other locations. Supported by the Municipal Art Society of New York.
  - The Street Life Project: Plaza Study Film, Silent, Color, 27 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1126)
  - Sunken Plazas, Other Places, Silent, Color, 6 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1128)
  - Triangulation, Silent, Color, 3 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1131)
  - Unedited Clips and Trims, All Unedited Clips and Trims are only available on original formats.
    - 100% AT SAKS (Reel AV 1456)
    - 100% CONVERSATIONS: LADIES AT 57TH & LEX (Reel AV 1443)
    - 2 PAIR MATRONS AND INSOLENT WOMAN (Reel AV 1448)
    - 53RD AND PARK: JUST STANDS THERE (Reel AV 1503)
    - A PALEY (Reel AV 1144)
    - BACKER AWARER ON 5TH (Reel AV 1484)
    - BLOOMINGDALE'S (Reel AV 1139)
    - BRANDYWINE - GOOD USE (Reel AV 1512)
    - CHARACTERS: COPS AND VENDORS (Reel AV 1457)
    - CITY HALL HISTORY (Reel AV 1496)
    - CONDENSED PLAZA: TIMELAPSE, CAMERAS, GROUPS, ETC (Reel AV 1142)
    - EMPHATIC HANDS (Reel AV 1498)
    - FAMILY-WEEKEND, JERSEY TURNPIKE (Reel AV 1490)
    - FAST BROWN & SLOW BLUE (Reel AV 1446, Reel AV 1488)
    - FEET AT THE PASS: LEX VEHICULAR (Reel AV 1433)
    - FEY BLONDE (Reel AV 1450)
    - GREEN HANDBILL PASSERS (Reel AV 1433)
    - HANDS (Reel AV 1135)
    - HANDS 2 (Reel AV 1136)
    - HANDS ASSEMBLY (Reel AV 1458, Reel AV 1475)
    - HANDBILLS: FRANK AND FRIENDS (Reel AV 1434)
    - HISTORIC 100%: TWO WOMEN AT 57TH (Reel AV 1444)
    - INCIDENTS & SCENICS/LOVERS (Reel AV 1465)
    - JERUSALEM (Reel AV 1455, Reel AV 1477)
    - JWB ROSSELLI AT 5105 (Reel AV 1485)
    - KEY ELEMENTS OF PILOT LEAD (Reel AV 1469)
    - LEXINGTON (Reel AV 1124)
    - LEX IN RAIN (Reel AV 1438)
    - LEX PEDESTRIANS AND VEHICULAR CROWDING (Reel AV 1453)
    - LIBRARY-BRYANT PARK (Reel AV 1478)
    - LINCOLN CENTER (Reel AV 1122)
    - LONDON: SMITHFIELD MEMS (Reel AV 1442)
    - LOVERS / EQUITABLE SCHMOOZERS (Reel AV 1501)
    - MAD CYCLISTS-PEDESTRIANS (Reel AV 1497)
    - MADISON AVE TIME LAPSE (Reel AV 1435)
    - MAGOO ON 5TH AND 50TH (Reel AV 1487)
    - MAGOO ON 6TH (Reel AV 1447)
    - MEN AND WOMEN: GIRL WATCHER (Reel AV 1460)
    - MUGGERS FROM 103 (Reel AV 1440)
    - NEGATIVE 1-2 (Reel AV 1471)
    - OLD LEAD (Reel AV 1133)
    - OLD PILOT LEAD (Reel AV 1473)
    - OPTICAL BLOWUP (Reel AV 1468)
    - OPTICAL BLOWUPS: SUPER 8 TO 16MM MASTER (Reel AV 1463)
    - ORIGINAL HISTORICAL PICTURES
    - OVERHEAD PEDESTRIANS, SHINY ... (Reel AV 1439)
    - PART 2 PILOT (Reel AV 1481)
    - PEDESTRIANS, JAYWALKERS, BOSTON REDS, ETC (Reel AV 1143)
    - PILOT A OUTTAKES (Reel AV 1140)
    - PILOT LEAD (Reel AV 1134)
    - PILOT LEAD ELEMENTS (Reel AV 1466)
    - PILOT OUTTAKES: TECHNIQUE, TIME LAPSE, MADISON MALL (Reel AV 1493)
    - PILOT PART 3 (Reel AV 1459)
    - PILOT-SEAGRAMS OUTTAKES #1 (Reel AV 1494)
    - PLAZA CONDENSED (Reel AV 1123)
    - PLAZA CONDENSED 2 (Reel AV 1137)
    - PLAZA, PART 3 (Reel AV 1130)
    - RASCALLY VENDOR AND COP AT ST. PATS (Reel AV 1437)
    - RETURN OF MAGOO (Reel AV 1436)
    - RIDE AERIAL (Reel AV 1513)
    - SAVE THE PORPOISE/ CYCLISTS (Reel AV 1500)
    - SCAVENGER (Reel AV 1480)
    - SCHMOOZING (Reel AV 1441)
    - SEAGRAMS LEDGE CHART (Reel AV 1449)
    - SITTING B (Reel AV 1461)
    - SPACING - CHAIR CHOOSING (Reel AV 1491)
    - ST. MARKS TIME LAPSE (Reel AV 1482)
    - STREET IN WINTER / SCHMOOZER A & B (Reel AV 1476)
    - STREET LIFE (Reel AV 1492)
    - STREET PEOPLE: KRISHNA, THINK, MAGOO (Reel AV 1141)
    - SUBLIMINAL RIALTOS (Reel AV 1462)
    - SUPER BASICS & MISC (Reel AV 1464)
    - SUPER HANDS & 100% (Reel AV 1467)
    - TECHNIQUE & TIME LAPSE (Reel AV 1479)
    - TERIMOA '81 PRINT: TOKYO (Reel AV 1489)
    - TOKYO I (Reel AV 1138)
    - TOKYO II (Reel AV 1495)
    - TOKYO PEDESTRIAN GAME (Reel AV 1472)
    - TRIANGULATION: SOHO TO BOSTON (Reel AV 1451)
    - TRIXIE AT LEX (Reel AV 1452)
    - TWO GUYS CAN'T SAY GOODBYE (Reel AV 1486)
    - TWO GUYS AT 57TH (Reel AV 1502)
    - TWO GUYS ON 57TH (Reel AV 1499)
    - VENICE: 100% AT SAKS (Reel AV 1456)
    - VENICE: DELAYED GOODBYE AND RIZITO (Reel AV 1445)
    - WALKING HANDS: SOAPBOXERS (Reel AV 1454)
    - WALKING HANDS ON 5TH, SLOB HANDS BEST (Reel AV 1483)
- General or Miscellaneous films, 23
  The original provenance, and/or specific association with RAC archival holdings, of the films presented in this series is unknown.
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower in Puerto Rico I, 1960 March 4; Some sound, Black & white and color, 10-15 minutes each. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1104, Reel AV 1615, Reel III 14.6-14, Reel III 14.6-13, Reel III 14.6-12, Reel AV 1105)
    President Eisenhower concludes a South America tour in Puerto Rico to address the American Assembly; luncheon, golfing at Dorado Beach Hotel.
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower in Puerto Rico II (III 14.6-13), 1960 March 4; Some sound, Black & white and color, 10-15 minutes each. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1104)
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower in Puerto Rico III (III 14.6-14), 1960 March 4; Some sound, Black & white and color, 10-15 minutes each. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1105)
  - The Effects of Morphine on Learned Adaptive Behavior and Experimental Neurosis in Cats, Silent, Black & white, 6 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1266)
    Film from the Neurophysiology Laboratories and the Division of Psychiatry at the Otho S.A. Sprague Memorial Institute and the University of Chicago. Summary of experimental work by Jules H. Masserman, M.D., University of Chicago, and Adam Wikler, M.D., U.S. Public Health Service. Contains some graphic footage of experiments on cats in a laboratory setting.
  - Eye on New York: The Forgotten River, 1965 October 31; Sound, Color, 30 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1641, Reel III 14.1 Ff 9)
    Episode about the Hudson River.
  - Golden Opportunities: Preservation of California Beaches and Parks, 1960s; Sound, Color, 12 minutes, only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1651, Reel III 14.6-9)
    Production about the population explosion in California. Visits to Seal Rock, Monte Rey, Spanish Mission, Sutter's Fort, Hearst Castle, and Redwood Forest. Narrated and produced by Walt Disney.
  - Grand Teton National Park, 1958; Silent, Color, 10 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel III 14.6-3, Reel AV 1616)
    Promotional film made by Frontier Airlines with scenes of horseback riding, river rafting, Jackson Lake Lodge, artist painting in the forest.
  - Henry Lends a Hand, 1952 November; Sound, Black & white, 700 ft/19 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel III 14.5-9, Reel AV 1699)
    short film about political volunteerism in America, made by the Committee for Political Education and Information.
  - Legislature Grants Privilege for Community to Vote for Progress, 1953 June 3; Sound, Black & white, 200 ft./6 minutes. Only available on 16mm film. (Reel III 14.9-2, Reel AV 1605)
    Westchester, NY towns of Tarrytown and North Tarrytown merger campaign
  - Peace Corps 2, Sound, Color, 6 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1115)
    A short NBC film about Peace Corp training, produced by the network
  - Time to Begin, 1965; Sound, Color, 28 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel III 14.4-1)
    short film produced by Colonial Williamsburg, Inc. for the Governor's Conference on Natural Beauty: threatened environment; potential loss of U.S. natural resources; pollution of land, water, etc.
  - Vacationland USA, Only available on original 16mm film (Reel III 14.6-4, Reel AV 1614)
    Warner Brothers tourism film showcasing Snake River, Grand Teton National Park, and includes the site of "Spencer's Mountain", a major Hollywood movie, with Arthur Godfrey, Henry Fonda, and Wally Cox.
  - Victory Clothing Drive, Sound, Black & white, 6 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 1946)
    Short promo spot featuring Spencer Tracey, encouraging Americans to donate clothes for European war victims.